Guide to the Cookie Teer Papers, 1971-2000, bulk 1983-1997 RL.01282
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cookie Teer papers
1971-2000, bulk 1983-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Teer, Dorothy "Cookie"
RL.01282
31.2 Linear Feet
Dorothy "Cookie" Foster Teer was born on August 15, 1941 to Dorothy and Nello Teer, Jr. of Durham, N.C. After a stint in New York, she returned to Durham in the 1970s. After taking some courses at Duke Divinity School, she joined the committee that founded Triangle Hospice. In the early 1980s, Teer became an overnight radical feminist, activist, and speaker, giving over 400 slide shows around the United States on pornography, sex role stereotyping, and child pornography. A 1987 conversation led to her co-founding of Southern Sisters Bookstore, a Durham, N.C. bookstore "by, for, and about women." By the late 1980s and 1990s, Teer was heavily involved in advocacy efforts around child custody, divorce, and domestic abuse, and frequently had "mothers on the run" living in her home. With a group of other women activists and radicals, Teer founded a writing collective called Women Against Sex. Married and divorced twice, Teer had three children. After Southern Sisters Bookstore closed, Teer took a step back from activism and began working as a real estate agent. The collection dates primarily between 1983-1997, providing thorough documentation of the social, cultural, and political debates over pornography in the United States in the 1980s and 1990s, with materials from both proponents and opponents of anti-pornography legislation, as well as detailed documentation of the pornography industry, and transcripts from hearings organized by the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography. The collection contains some materials related to particular feminist activists and theorists, including Nikki Craft, Catherine MacKinnon, and Andrea Dworkin. Teer's extensive subject files also contain clippings, correspondence, and printed materials pertaining to women's rights, feminists, feminist organizations and events, and social issues related to women and children such as rape, pornography, incest, prostitution, domestic violence, child custody, and child abuse. Other materials relate to her ownership of the Southern Sisters bookstore (Durham, N.C.), such as promotional materials, newsletters, events fliers, and calendars.
23,400 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection has restrictions
Materials related to Teer's friendship with Andrea Dworkin are closed. With this exception, the collection is open to research.
Some materials have been redacted to remove sensitive information such as credit card numbers. Originals of redacted material are not available for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Cookie Teer Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003.
Biographical Note
Dorothy "Cookie" Foster Teer was born on August 15, 1941 to Dorothy and Nello Teer, Jr. of Durham, N.C. After a stint in New York, she returned to Durham in the 1970s to go into business. After taking some courses at Duke Divinity School, she joined the committee that founded Triangle Hospice. In the early 1980s, Teer became an overnight radical feminist, activist, and speaker, giving over 400 slide shows around the United States on pornography, sex role stereotyping, and child pornography. A 1987 dinner conversation led to her co-founding of Southern Sisters Bookstore, a Durham, N.C. bookstore "by, for, and about women" that served as a haven for activism and women's experiences. By the late 1980s and 1990s, Teer was heavily involved in advocacy efforts around child custody, divorce, and domestic abuse, and frequently had "mothers on the run" living in her home. With a group of other women activists and radicals, Teer founded a writing collective called Women Against Sex; they gave a paper at a conference in New York with the same title, which is still printed in anthologies. Married and divorced twice, Teer had three children. After Southern Sisters Bookstore closed, Teer took a step back from activism, and began working as a real estate agent who, with a woman builder friend, restored and sold old houses.
Chronology
1945, Aug. 15 Born in Durham, N.C.
1960-1962 Attended Finch College, New York, N.Y.
1962-1964 Attended University of North Carolina - Chapel Hill
1971-1978 Co-owner and Vice President, Vestido, Inc., Chapel Hill, N.C. and Atlanta, Ga.
1978 Founding member, Triangle Hospice, N.C.
1979-1985 Triangle Hospice Patient and Family Volunteer, N.C.
1980-1983 Triangle Hospice Director of Development, N.C.
1981-1984 Triangle Hospice Special Events Coordinator, N.C.
1981-1986 Member N.C. N.O.W. Task Force on Violence Against Women (Chair 1985-1986)
1983-1987 Received funding grants for contested child custody cases in Orange County, N.C. courts, resulting in the 1991 book Gender Bias, the Family and the Law.
1983-1993 Co-founder, Pornography Awareness, Inc.
1985 Jan. Founder and Chair, "Is There a Relationship Between Pornography and Sexual Violence" symposium, Duke University, Durham, N.C.
1985 Oct. Founder and Chair, "Women Surviving: Cultural Patterns" symposium, North Carolina Central University, Durham, N.C.
1985-1990 National Anti-Pornography Civil Rights Steering Committee
1986 Co-founded A Southern Women's Writing Collective
1986-1991 Duke University Council for Women's Studies
1987 Co-founder of N.C. Mobilization Action Project, N.C. Marital Rape Law
1987-1988 Served on Board of Directors, Orange County Planned Parenthood, N.C.
1987-1990 Member of Durham Orange Battered Women's Coalition, N.C.
1988-1992 Served as Orange County Human Relations Commissioner, N.C.
1988-1995 Acted as co-founder, President, and CEO of Southern Sisters Bookstore, Durham, N.C.
1989 Chair and organizer, Orange County Human Relations Committee hearings, "Quality and Status of Life for Women and Children in Orange County," N.C.
1989-1990 Co-founded Orange County Committee for Justice for Women, Orange County, N.C.
1989 Served on Board of Directors of Orange County Women's Center, N.C.
1990-1992 Co-authored Orange County Human Rights Code, Orange County, N.C.
Collection Overview
The materials in the Dorothy "Cookie" Teer Papers date from 1971 to 2000, with the bulk of the collection dating between 1983 and 1997. These materials include: newspaper clippings, magazines, correspondence, photographs, meeting minutes, manuscripts, notes, published books, audio and videotapes, organizational records, and court transcripts. The collection documents Teer's activism during this period, the feminist issues with which she was concerned, feminist and anti-pornography activism in and around Chapel Hill and Durham, N.C., and the activities of the organizations of which Teer was a member, including the National Organization for Women (N.O.W.) and Pornography Awareness.
This collection provides thorough documentation of the social, cultural, and political debates over pornography in the United States in the 1980s and 1990s, with materials from both proponents and opponents of anti-pornography legislation, as well as detailed documentation of the pornography industry, with a focus on publications such as Playboy and Hustler. Transcripts from hearings organized by the Attorney General's Commission on Pornography supplement these materials, with testimony from all sides of the pornography debate. The collection contains some materials related to particular feminist activists and theorists, including Nikki Craft, Catherine MacKinnon, and Andrea Dworkin. Teer's extensive subject files also contain newspaper and magazine clippings, correspondence, and printed items pertaining to women's rights, feminists, feminist organizations and events, and social issues related to women and children such as rape, pornography, incest, prostitution, domestic violence, child custody, and child abuse. Other materials relate to her ownership of the Southern Sisters bookstore (Durham, N.C.), such as promotional materials, newsletters, events fliers, several rolodex files, rubber stamps, and calendars.
The collection is organized into four series: Subject Files, Orange County Human Relations Commission, Attorney General's Commission on Pornography, and Southern Sisters Bookstore.
The Subject Files series contains clippings and academic articles related to violence against women and children. Other materials include extensive documentation of the anti-pornography movement, the work of the Orange County Human Relations Commission, the National Organization for Women (N.O.W.), and various feminist or anti-pornography symposia. Includes files on feminist artist and activist Nikki Craft and feminist scholar and lawyer Catherine MacKinnon. Several files relate to the women's/feminist Southern Sisters Bookstore in Durham, N.C., of which Teer was a proprietor.
The Orange County Human Relations Commission series contains materials related to the Orange County Human Relations Commission and the Committee for Justice for Women of Orange County. Some materials consist of pamphlets or news clippings related to the HRC's focus areas, especially the status of women and children within the county and the state; series also contains planning for and documentation of the public hearings on the status of women and children in Orange County, N.C., organized by the Human Relations Commission and held in 1989.
The Attorney General's Commission on Pornography series contains materials related to the commission's 1985-1986 investigation into pornography. Consisting almost entirely of transcripts from public hearings on pornography, some with annotations, this series details many aspects of the U.S. pornography industry. This series also contains some materials from the 1983 Minneapolis hearings on pornography.
The Southern Sisters Bookstore series contains materials related to the feminist/women's Southern Sisters Bookstore, of which Teer was co-owner, President, and CEO. Materials include financial records, flyers, mailing lists, mission statement, bibliographies of materials related to feminist issues, as well as materials such as cards from the bookstore's Rolodex, signs, and rubber stamps. Contains some correspondence from patrons, donors, and supporters of the store.
Child pornography -- United States; Child sexual abuse -- United States; Women political activists -- United States; Booksellers and bookselling -- North Carolina -- Durham; Pornography -- Censorship; Pornography -- Law and legislation -- United States; Custody of children -- United States; Domestic violence -- United States; Serial murderers; Violence in mass media; Pornography -- Psychological aspects; Prostitution -- United States; Women in the book industries and trade -- United States; Clippings (information artifacts); Fliers (printed matter); National Organization for Women; Teer, Dorothy "Cookie"; Southern Sisters Bookstore; MacKinnon, Catharine A.; Teer, Dorothy "Cookie"; Dworkin, Andrea; United States. Attorney General's Commission on Pornography; Women Against Pornography
- Subject Files Series, 1971-2000, 37 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The Subject Files Series contains newspaper and magazine clippings related to violence against women and children, including materials on child abuse, child sexual abuse, rape, pornography, child custody, battered women, incest, and trafficking, as well as some academic articles on these topics. Other materials include extensive documentation of the anti-pornography movement, including materials from Teer's involvement in Pornography Awareness, and publications and correspondence from other groups such as Women Against Pornography. Includes some documentation of anti-pornography protests, especially in and around Chapel Hill, N.C., and of the proposed Anti-Pornography Civil Rights Ordinance. Some topical materials address the work of the Orange County Human Relations Commission, of which Teer was a member; more on this topic can be found in the Orange County Human Relations Commission Series.
  Other materials include copies of Teer's speeches on various topics, correspondence, and letters to editors. Some materials document some of the work of the National Organization for Women (N.O.W.), North Carolina's chapter of N.O.W., and Chapel Hill N.O.W., and various feminist or anti-pornography symposia organized by or attended by Teer.
  This series also includes multiple folders of materials documenting the work of feminist artist and activist Nikki Craft, as well as significant material documenting the work and writing of feminist scholar and lawyer Catherine MacKinnon. Finally, several files relate to the women's/feminist Southern Sisters Bookstore in Durham, N.C., of which Teer was a proprietor. More materials on Southern Sisters Bookstore can be found in the Southern Sisters Series.
  Arrangement note
  Arrangement is primarily alphabetical. Teer's original folder titles and organizational scheme were largely retained, with minimal revisions for purposes of clarity.
  - "Victims of Pornography," 1991 Dec. 13 (Box 1)
  - Abortion Rights, 1971-1988 (Box 1)
  - Adam & Eve/HE, Inc., 1986-1993 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Carol, 1990-1998 (Box 1)
  - Adventure trips - women, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Advertising, false (Box 1)
  - Advertising - target groups, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Advertising, tobacco - target groups, 1987 (Box 1)
  - ACLU, 1985-1995 (Box 1)
  - AIDS, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - AIDS - changing lifestyles due to fear of, 1987 (Box 1)
  - AIDS in children, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Alcoholism, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Alward, Lori, 1990-1998 (Box 1)
  - Animal rights, 1983-1993 (Box 1)
  - Amnesty/torture (men), 1986 (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Michelle, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Anti-porn M.D.s, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Anti-porn/ anti-rape (men) (Box 1)
  - Anti-semitism, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - American Psychiatric Association Violence Seminar, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Approaches to porn (Legislation - Jamie Moore) (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, Louise, 1990 Mar. (Box 1)
  - Asian porn, 1991-1997 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Meg, 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Meg, Women and the Law, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Meg, on children, on prostitution, Winnebago case, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Barry, Kathleen, 1985-1991 (Box 2)
  - Barry, Kathleen - pornography (Box 2)
  - Bart, Pauline (Box 2)
  - Battered women, 1983-1999 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Battered women - violent crime, domestic violence, 1981-1997 (Box 2)
  - Battered women - O.J. Simpson, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Bellingham, Washington, 1988-1992 (Box 2)
  - Bellingham decision, 1989 Feb. 9 (Box 2)
  - Beauty pageants, 1985-1992 (Box 2)
  - Berry, Mary F., 1985 (Box 2)
  - Bibliographies (Box 2)
  - Bingham, Sallie (Box 2)
  - Boat, Barbara, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Book reviews, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Brides business, 1986-1991 (Box 2)
  - Burgess, Ann and Ken Lanning (Box 2)
  - Butler, Twiss, 1986-1991 (Box 3)
  - Butler, Twiss - NOW insurance discrimination (Box 3)
  - California Women's Law Conference, 1987 Aug. 28-30 (Box 3)
  - Cambridge ordinance/ organizations, 1986-1990 (Box 3)
  - Card, Claudia - "Responsibility and Moral Luck" (Box 3)
  - Cartoons (Box 3)
  - Censorship (general), 1986 (Box 3)
  - Censorship, Atlanta Magazine, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Censorship, books, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Censorship on campus, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Censorship trials and law suits (Box 3)
  - Chalfie, Debbie, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Chance, Zoe, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Changing Men, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Check & Sommers, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Chesler, Phyllis, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Chicago organizing, 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Chicago, Judy, 1980-1990 (Box 3)
  - Churches Against Porn, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Circumcision, 1987-1997 (Box 3)
  - Civil court cases, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Civil disobedience (Box 3)
  - Child abuse - Lanning profile (Box 3)
  - Child advocacy, 1986-1990 (Box 3)
  - Child advocacy - PACA/ Jeanne Lenzer (Box 3)
  - Child advertising, 1991-1999 (Box 3)
  - Advocacy - child's rights/ law suits, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
  - Child advocacy (Box 3)
  - Child brides (Box 3)
  - Child custody, 1984-1995 (Box 3)
  - Child custody - Orange County (Box 3)
  - Committee for Justice for Women of Orange County/ legal clinic (Box 4)
  - Jones, Ellie, 1989-1991 (Box 4)
  - Child - hearings on pornography, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Child incest bibliography, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Child incest, facts and statistics (Box 4)
  - Child incest and pornography – Finkelhor (Box 4)
  - Child incest, multiple personality (Box 4)
  - Child incest, 1985-1991 (Box 4)
  - Child incest, mothers of, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Child incest, mothers on the run (Box 4)
  - Incest, mother of child victim – LaLonde, Virginia (Box 4)
  - Child incest - mothers who kill (Box 4)
  - Incest (Box 4)
  - Child incest - perpetrators (Box 4)
  - Child physical abuse, 1986-1996 (Box 4)
  - Child porn – court decisions (Box 4)
  - Child porn – photography (Box 4)
  - Child porn – Wonderland (Box 4)
  - Child poverty/starvation (Box 4)
  - Child sexual abuse, 1984-1998 (Box 4)
  - Child sexual abuse – perpetrators, 1987-1997 (Box 4)
  - Child sexual abuse – child abuse, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Violent crime – perpetrators, 1982-1988 (Box 4)
  - Violence committed by children (Box 4)
  - Child abuse, ritual (Box 4)
  - Child abuse – Satanism/ritual abuse (Box 5)
  - Orange County Child Sexual Abuse Task Force (Box 5)
  - Child pornography commentary (Box 5)
  - Child porn laws, 1984-1990 (Box 5)
  - Child porn perpetrators, 1985-1990 (Box 5)
  - Child sexual abuse by educators, 1984-1995 (Box 5)
  - Child sexual assault prevention (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Missing children/reporting abuse law (Box 5)
  - Child survivors of prostitution and pornography (Box 5)
  - Child prostitution, 1986-1992 (Box 5)
  - Child Victimization inN.C. report, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Sexual trafficking of children in N.C., 1987 May (Box 5)
  - Children of the night, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Children of the night – Abel-Peterson, Trudee – Runaways, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Children of the night – The Plain Truth, 1989 May/June (Box 5)
  - Children of the night – Covenant House/Ritter (Box 5)
  - Honor ribbon (Box 5)
  - Cline, Victor – empirical evidence (Box 5)
  - Clinical articles – rape, incest, etc. (Box 5)
  - Clinical articles (Box 5)
  - [CLOSED: Items in Box 6 are closed to research] (Box 6)
  - Dworkin letters, 1984-2000 (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Dworkin – Hustler suit (Box 6)
  - Dworkin – men possessing women (Box 6)
  - Dworkin – why porn matters to feminists – Penthouse "interview," 1987 April (Box 6)
  - Dworkin – "Why Pornography Matters to Feminists" (Box 6)
  - Dworkin – why porn matters to feminists – wife battering (Box 6)
  - Dworkin – press coverage, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
  - Dworkin – press coverage – Ice and Fire, Intercourse (Box 6)
  - Dworkin – press coverage (Box 6)
  - Dworkin letter, 1992 October 19 (Box 6)
  - Clinton, Bill, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Political leaders abuse of women (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 7)
  - Cookie's talks, 1986-1999 (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Cookie's talks (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Cookie's press coverage (Box 7)
  - Correspondence/Cookie's talks (Box 7)
  - Notebooks (Box 7)
  - Letters to the editor, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Cookie's talks – child sexual abuse (Box 7)
  - Cookie's talks – CR ordinance (Box 7)
  - Cookie – articles, etc., 1992 (Box 7)
  - Cookie's talks – civil rights ordinance (Box 8)
  - Cookie – vitae, P.A. info (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous notebook (Box 8)
  - Commission on Pornography, 1985 (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Commission articles, 1985-1986 (Box 8)
  - Commission articles – NAPCRO – feminist response to A.G. Commission on Porn, 1986 July (Box 8)
  - Community activism and action – Pornography Resource Center (PRC) – comparable worth (Box 8)
  - Community activism and action – PRC – congressional correspondence, McCain et. al., 1985 (Box 8)
  - Community activism and action – PRC – Concerned Charlotteans (Box 8)
  - Community activism and action – PRC – conservatives – Concerned Charlotteans, 1985-1989 (Box 8)
  - Conservatives, 1985-1991 (Box 9)
  - Conservatives – Eagle Forum (Box 9)
  - Conservatives – National Federation for Decency (Box 9)
  - Coyote, 1986 (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – flyers (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – Guccione posters (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – Meredith Corporation (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – Myth California, 1983 (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – naturist (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki II (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – Penthouse rampage (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – Iconoclast, 1988-1991 (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – rape manual and stickers (Box 9)
  - Craft, Nikki – miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Cross burning, 1991 (Box 10)
  - Crime statistics (Box 10)
  - Crisp, Helen (Box 10)
  - Crowther, Hal – Spectator, 1988 (Box 10)
  - Daily Tar Heel (Box 10)
  - B. Dalton action, 1985 (Box 10)
  - Davis, Karen (Box 10)
  - Dershowitz, Alan, 1991 (Box 10)
  - Disability (Box 10)
  - Diamond – "Pornography and Repression" (Box 10)
  - Discrimination against college women, 1987 (Box 10)
  - Discrimination against women (Box 10)
  - Dispute Settlement Center, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Domestic workers organization (Box 10)
  - Donnerstein – erotica and aggression (Box 10)
  - Duke Child Protection Team (Box 10)
  - Duke Women's Studies, 1987-1990 (Box 10)
  - Duke University Women's Studies (Box 10)
  - Duke University Women's Studies – Council on Women's Studies, 1987 Fall (Box 10)
  - Durham battered women (Box 10)
  - Durham and Chapel Hill ordinance – cable porn – letter to Durham City Council (Box 10)
  - Durham – juvenile crime, 1988 (Box 10)
  - Easley, Mike, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
  - Elshtain, Jean Bethke (Box 10)
  - Ellman, Amy (Box 10)
  - Erotica/differences – Gloria Steinem (Box 11)
  - Feminist Anti-Censorship Taskforce (F.A.C.T.) (Box 11)
  - F.A.C.T. 2 (Box 11)
  - Feminists for Free Expression (Box 11)
  - Fact/fiction (Box 11)
  - Feminists Against Pornography (F.A.P.) Chicago (Box 11)
  - Fathers' rights (Box 11)
  - Female entertainment – strip, topless joints (Box 11)
  - Feminists Fighting Pornography (Box 11)
  - Fetal/baby (Box 11)
  - Fetal/baby – child development (Box 11)
  - Fewel, Jean, 1988 (Box 11)
  - Fewel case – violent crime victims (Box 11)
  - Film comment (Box 11)
  - Fowler's action, 1984 (Box 11)
  - Fox, Carl (Box 11)
  - Frick, Donna/Smith (Box 11)
  - The Front Page, 1985-1989 (Box 11)
  - Fulani, Lenora (Box 11)
  - Gay men (Box 11)
  - Gay men – Lambda Rising, etc. (Box 11)
  - Gay men – Mapplethorpe, Robert (Box 11)
  - General articles (Box 11)
  - Global Fund for Women (Box 11)
  - Goldsmith, J. – porn testimony, juvenile justice, 1984 Sept. (Box 11)
  - Grant writing (Box 11)
  - Gray and Company (Box 11)
  - Green River murders, 1985-1989 (Box 11)
  - Hahn, Jessica and Jim Bakker, 1987 (Box 11)
  - Handler, Michelle (Box 11)
  - Harris, Trish, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Hate crimes, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Biden – hate violence against women bill (Box 12)
  - Hate literature bill from England (Box 12)
  - Haug, Frigga (Box 12)
  - Hazing (Box 12)
  - Helen X., 1989 Oct. (Box 12)
  - Heller, Valerie (Box 12)
  - Herman, Judy (Box 12)
  - High Society Magazine (Box 12)
  - Hill-Teer legislative cocktail party (Box 12)
  - History of women's rights (Box 12)
  - Holmbeck, Paul (Box 12)
  - Homeless women, 1987 (Box 12)
  - Hopwood, Kathy – self-defense, 1990-1991 (Box 12)
  - Hustler Magazine, 1987-1997 (Box 12)
  - Internet (Box 12)